<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bhaskar Karambelkar&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/konkan/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Bhaskar Karambelkar&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Bhaskar V. Karambelkar</copyright>
    <atom:link href="/tags/konkan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Beautiful Konkan</title>
      <link>/2009/02/beautiful-konkan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2009 08:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2009/02/beautiful-konkan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From long deserted beaches &amp;amp; clear blue green waters, to lush green coconut trees, Konkan has it all. The Konkan region lies on the west cost of the Maharashtra state of India, along the Aribean sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;lthough not as famous amongst tourists as &amp;ldquo;Goa&amp;rdquo;, the konkan region is full of places to explore, from historic temples, to picturesque beaches, to dense jungles and not to mention the rich history of the &amp;ldquo;Maratha Empire&amp;rdquo; still echoing from the numerous mountains, hills, valleys, &amp;amp; gorges of the Sahyandries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; was fortunate enough to visit the &amp;ldquo;Sindhudurga&amp;rdquo; district in Jan &amp;lsquo;09, during my vacation, and got some nice pictures of this fascinating land. Within a short span of 2-3 days, we were able to explore a lot of interesting places and learn a lot of fascinating history of this district. The beautiful beaches at Vengurla &amp;amp; Kunkeshwar, to the historic temples at Mangaon, Arawli, Akeri &amp;amp; Aachara, the ever so beautiful &amp;ldquo;Hiranyakeshi&amp;rdquo; river. Also the best of Sahayandries at &amp;ldquo;Amboli Ghat&amp;rdquo; , &amp;ldquo;Saat Kawale (Seven crows) point&amp;rdquo;. The awe-inspiring sea fort at Malwan. Not to mention the various small and large villages along the way and some mouth water &amp;ldquo;Malwani&amp;rdquo; cuisine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to enjoy these memories of mine, and if possible visit the place your self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;//photos.karambelkar.info/frame/slideshow?key=s36GCg&amp;captions=1&amp;autoStart=0&amp;navigation=1&amp;playButton=1&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; height=&#34;600&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>